<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Spiritual or heavenly salutation to all the tender-hearted in Christendom that are seeking the kingdom of God and the righteousness therof which I desire and intreat them to read over these following lines in the love of God, in which they are sent to them from him that desires the good of all mankind here, and their eternal happiness hereafter / [by] George Fox.</title>
            <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1919</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36423</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15690439</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15690439</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104396</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1593:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Spiritual or heavenly salutation to all the tender-hearted in Christendom that are seeking the kingdom of God and the righteousness therof which I desire and intreat them to read over these following lines in the love of God, in which they are sent to them from him that desires the good of all mankind here, and their eternal happiness hereafter / [by] George Fox.</title>
                  <author>Fox, George, 1624-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXIX [1679]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through and loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104396:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A Spiritual or Heavenly SALUTATION To all the Tender-hearted in CHRISTENDOM, That are ſeeking the Kingdom of God and the Righteouſneſs thereof, which I deſire and intreat them to Read over theſe following Lines, in the love of God, in which they are ſent to them from him that deſires the good of all Mankind here, and their Eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs hereafter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GEORGE FOX.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Northcoot</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lumbard-ſtreet</hi> 1690.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104396:2"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104396:2"/>
                  <head>A SPIRITUAL or HEAVENLY Salutation, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>TO all the tender Hearted in Chriſtendom, whoſe Faces are turned towards Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and whoſe Minds are turned and drawn by the Spirit of God to Chriſt, who is the new and living way to God, and the one Mediator betwixt God and Man; who enlightneth every one that cometh into the World, with his Heavenly Divine Light, which is the life in Chriſt the Word, by whom all things were Made and Created; Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Believe in the Light, that ye may become Children of the Light,</hi> ſo Chriſt who is not of the World but from above, hath given us his Light to believe in, and to walk in, that we may have the Light of life, and he that believeth is a Child of Light and born of God, and overcomes the World; and paſſes from the Death that came by <hi>Adam,</hi> and is engrafted into Chriſt the life, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> and ſo are living Stones or Members of him the living Head; and the Children of this Light that walk in this Light, have fellowſhip with the Son, and the Father, and one with another; and all Chriſtendom that walk not in the Light that Chriſt hath given you, are not in this Heavenly Divine fellowſhip. But this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie we do witneſs fulfilled and fulfilling concerning Chriſt; God ſaid, I will give him for a Covenant of the People, <hi>and a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104396:3"/>
Light to the Gentiles, and he ſhall be my Salvation to the ends of the Earth,</hi> Iſa. 49.6, 8. So that they that come to know their Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and into Covenant with God, they muſt come into the Light of Chriſt which giveth the Light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the face of Chriſt Jeſus, which Light ſhines in their Hearts, the Heavenly treaſure in the Earthen Veſſels; and if all that is called Chriſtendom, had believed in the Light, the life in Chriſt, which Chriſt giveth and teacheth to Believe in that which he giveth them, then had they been all Children of the Light, and of the Day of Chriſt, in Unity and Fellowſhip in the Light, and then they had not made ſo many Faiths and Beliefs which they have deſtroyed one another about. And if all Chriſtendom had obſerved the Apoſtles Doctrin to the Church of Chriſt, who exhorted them to <hi>look to Jeſus the Author and finiſher of their Faith,</hi> then they would not have made ſo many Faiths, about which they have Perſecuted one another: Whereas no manner of Men below, can make a Catholick Divine Faith; for I ſay, that Chriſt Jeſus is the Beginner and Finiſher of our Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Divine, Precious, Catholick or Univerſal Faith, which he the Holy one, doth reveal from Faith to Faith; and the Myſtery of this holy Faith is held in a pure Conſcience, and not in an impure one; and it purifies the Heart and gives Victory over that which diſpleaſes God, and ſeparates from God, in which holy Faith, which we have from the holy One, we pleaſe the holy God which gives us the Victory over that which diſpleaſes him, and ſeparates from him, and have acceſs to him: In this holy Divine Faith is our Unity; ſo Chriſt has the honour, who is the Author of our Faith, and Finiſher of it, and likewiſe gives us his Light; the Life in himſelf; ſo he is the Author of our Belief to Believe in. —And happy had all Chriſtendom been, had they kept to the Apoſtles Doctrin, to the Church of Chriſt, who ſaid, <hi>the Grace of God that bringeth Salvation, hath appeared unto all men, and teacheth us,</hi> namely Chriſtians, then and now, <hi>to live Godly, Righteouſly, and Soberly, and deny <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouneſs and Worldly Luſts.</hi> Now I ſay, happy had all Chriſtians been ſince the Apoſtles days, if they had kept to this Grace of God their teacher, which would have brought their Salvation, and would have brought them into Favour with God; if they had,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104396:3"/>
then there would not have been ſo many itching Ears, and have ſet up ſo many Schools and Colledges to make Teachers, which brings Chriſtendom into confuſion one againſt another. Some may ſay, <hi>is this Grace ſufficient?</hi> God ſaid to <hi>Paul,</hi> it was ſufficient, when he was in his Tryals and Temptations; and Thouſands can Witneſs, that the Grace of God is ſufficient, and doth teach them what to deny, and how to live, and doth bring their Salvation; for as the Law came by <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and the Jews were to live under it; and Grace and Truth is come by Jeſus in the New Teſtament, and this Grace and Truth is in the Hearts of Gods People, and they are under Grace's teaching, and in the Covenant of Grace; for Chriſt by the Grace of God taſted Death for every man, that they may all come out of the Death in <hi>Adam,</hi> to the Light and Life in him; by his Light, Grace, Truth, and Faith in their Hearts; that he is the Author of; for there is a Prophecy in <hi>Joel, That God would pour out his ſpirit upon all fleſh,</hi> which the Apoſtles, in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. ſhew the fulfilling of to the Jews; and now, what is the matter that all the Sons, Daughters, Servants, Hand-maids, and Old-men in Chriſtendom, have not their Heavenly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies, Viſions, and Dreams? Is it not becauſe they have erred from the Spirit of God, and vex, quench, and grieve it, that he hath poured upon them, and become like the Jews; to whom God gave his good Spirit, but they Rebelled againſt it? there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is not all Chriſtendom on heaps one againſt another, out of fellowſhip? therefore the means by which all Chriſtendom, and all People are to come into Unity and Fellowſhip in the Spirit, is, that they muſt Come all into the Spirit that God hath poured upon them, by which Spirit they muſt be Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed; and have the Body of Sin and Death cut off, which they came into by Tranſgreſſion in <hi>Adam,</hi> who had none before he fell; and they muſt be Baptiſed with the Spirit, to plunge down Sin by this Spirit; I ſay, all muſt be Baptiſed into one Body, and ſo all to Drink into one Spirit; this Spirit of God brings all into Fellowſhip and Unity, for the <hi>Spirit of God is the bond of Peace,</hi> and in it is the profiting; and it openeth the Heavenly Prophecies, Viſions, and Dreams to Gods People now, as it did in the Apoſtles days. Chriſt Jeſus ſet up a Worſhip
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104396:4"/>
above Sixteen hundred Years agoe, in the Spirit and in the Truth, when he put down the <hi>Jews</hi> Worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the <hi>Samarinus</hi> at <hi>Jacob</hi>'s-<hi>Well,</hi> and ſaid; <hi>The hour cometh, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, that they that worſhip the Father, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth, for ſuch he ſeeketh to worſhip him;</hi> and therefore all muſt come to the Spirit of God and his Truth in their Hearts, by which Truth and Spirit in their Hearts, they muſt know the God of Truth an infinite Spirit, and in his Truth and in his Spirit, to Worſhip and Serve the God of Truth. And if all Chriſtendom had kept to the Truth and Spirit in their Hearts, they had kept to the Worſhip that Chriſt, the Lord from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven had ſet up (for none can ſet up a better than he) and then they had not ſet up ſo many Worſhips, and Perſecuted one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther about them; but all People muſt return to the Spirit of God and the Truth in their Hearts, if they will Serve and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God their Creator; for God is come to teach his People himſelf, by his Son; for as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>God at ſundry times and in divers manners, ſpake to the Fathers by the Prophets, but now in theſe laſt days God hath ſpoken to us by his Son,</hi> who bruiſes the Serp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ts head, who hath been the head of all falſe Speakers and falſe Religions, Churches, Ways and Worſhips; but God is the Speaker now to his People, by his Son, who was the Speaker to <hi>Adam</hi> in Paradiſe, but when <hi>Adam</hi> forſook Gods Teaching, and followed the Serpents, he loſt his happineſs, ſo have the Jews and the Chriſtians; therefore all muſt return by the Spirit, Light, Grace, and Truth of Jeſus, to Chriſt Jeſus the great Prophet, Shepherd, Biſhop, Leader, and Counſellor, that they may hear God ſpeak to them by his Son, <hi>and he that hath the Son hath Life, and he that hath not the Son hath not Life,</hi> though he may make a profeſſion of all the Scriptures: And none can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Son, but by the Light, Grace, and Truth that comes from him, in their Hearts. Why are not all Chriſtendom the Sons and Daughters of God, which make a Profeſſion of Chriſt? Is it not becauſe they do not receive Chriſt, in his Grace and Truth in their Hearts, which comes from him? For <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> by eating of that which God forbid, brought Death on them and their Poſterity; and now Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That he is the Bread from Heaven, and except they eat this Bread
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104396:4"/>
from Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that he gives, they have not Life in him;</hi> ſo by eating came Death, and by eating comes Life again, it is not by talking. And he gives his Bread from Heaven now, for he is the Heavenly Bread, Rock, and Foundation, Chriſt the ſame to day as yeſterday, and ſo for ever, to all his People, who was Dead and is alive again, and Lives for evermore, and Reigns in his People. And now in this Goſpel day, of Chriſt the new Covenant: God writes his Law in the Hearts of his People, and puts it in their Minds, that all ſhould know him from the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the leaſt, and none need ſay to his Brother, know the Lord, which thouſands do witneſs this Law of Love, Faith and Life, that all may read what God puts in their Minds, and writes in their Hearts, and ſuch are heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>'s Children, who is the Mother of them all; and no Mother can they own below the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as the Chriſtians did in the Primitive Times, and ſuch are the Church of the firſt Born written in Heaven, cloathed with the Sun and the Moon under her Feet, all changeable Churches, Ways, Worſhips, Religions and Teachers, all which change as changeable things, for the Moon changes, but the Sun doth not change but cloaths his living Members, who is over his Houſe; the Royal Prieſthood offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up ſpiritual Sacrifices to God (not Carnal) by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>And when Chriſt ſent his Diſciples to preach the Goſpel to every Creature under Heaven: It was not with the Penalty of Priſons, Gallows, Fire, and ſpoiling of the Goods of them that would not believe and receive them. And therefore it is time for all that profeſs Chriſtianity, to put up the Carnal Sword concerning Religion, and obey Chriſt's Command, who ſaid he came not to deſtroy Men's Lives, but to ſave them; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore love God and Chriſt, and one another, and Enemies, for Love and Charity is the moſt Excellent way above all tinkling Cymbals, and ſounding Braſs; for they that dwell in Love dwell in God.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104396:5"/>
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>AND all you Teachers that make a Scoff and a Mock at the Motion, or moving of the Spirit of God; but you had never had the Holy Scriptures which you make a Trade of, had not the Holy Men of God ſpoken them forth as they were moved by the Holy Spirit of God, and this ſhews that you are erred from the Holy Spirit of God, that the Apoſtles were in, and the moving of it, and fellowſhip in it, which proceedeth from the Father and the Son: And as the Apoſtle ſaid to the Church of Chriſt, <hi>That I may know him, and the Power of his Reſurrection, and the Fellowſhip of his Sufferings, being made conformable unto his Death,</hi> Phil. 3.10. This is the right Knowledge of Chriſt, and the true Conformity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they that are conformable to Chriſt, who faith, he is from above and not of this World, ſuch are not conformable to this World.</p>
                  <p>And now all you that go under the Name of Chriſtians, <hi>Let every one that nameth the Name of Chriſt depart from Iniquity,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.19. <hi>And if any Man have not the Spirit of Chriſt he is none of his,</hi> Rom. 8.9. And the Apoſtle tells the Church of Chriſt, <hi>That no Man can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> 1. Cor. 12.3. <hi>And the Holy Ghoſt proceedeth from the Father and the Son,</hi> John 15.26. And again the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Corinthians, Examine your ſelves whether you be in the Faith, prove your own ſelves; know ye not your own ſelves, how that Jeſus Chriſt is in you, except you be Reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. And again the Apoſtle ſaith to the <hi>Romans, The Word is nigh thee, even in thy Mouth, and in thy Heart, and this is the Word of Faith which we preach,</hi> Rom. 10.8. And again the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The Myſtery which hath been from Ages and Generations, but now is manifeſt unto the Saints; to whom God would make known what is the Riches of</hi>
                  </p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="lat">
            <body>
               <div type="fragmentary_text">
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:104396:5"/>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                     <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <p>amabo oſcultate: Salemque quo cuncta quae ſapiunt dignoſcatis in vobiſmet retinete; nec minus Oleum in lampadibus veſtris ſemper habete, ut fatuis virginibus abſimiles ſitis: Talenta vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis concredita occupantes Pigri ſervi cenſuram evitabitis; decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio enim Spiritus Dei unicuique ad proficiendum datur: Nec ſitis locutores, aut verbi Dei tantum auditores, verum illius vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatis Executores ne veſtras ſeducatis animas ſemper voſmet perhibete: Religioſus enim cultus &amp; incontaminatus apud De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um &amp; Patrem hic eſt, inviſere Orphanos &amp; Viduas in afflictione ipſorum &amp; immaculatum ſeſe conſervare a mundo: Omnes qui Chriſtianam profeſſionem profitentur hunc cultum Religioſum a mundi maculis immunes reddentem colere oportet; haec enim Religio omnibus mundi Religionibus maculoſis preſtantior, ſuum cultorem mitem, tenerumque efficit; in quem ſtatum, ut omnes dicti Chriſtiani tandem perveniant, Deum omnipotentem ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nixe rogatum habeo.</p>
                  <p>Apoſtolus Chriſtianis veris pronunciavit, vos eſtis Templum Dei viventis, ſicut dixit Deus, habitabo in eis &amp; inambulabo, &amp; ero illorum Deus &amp; ipſi erunt mihi Populus. An ignoratis Corpus veſtrum eſſe templum Spiritus Sancti qui eſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>bis, quem habetis a Deo, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. &amp; 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. Chriſtianitatis Profeſſores ubivis gentium hanc notitiam ſibi ratam debent habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, quod nimirum Corpora earum ſint templa Dei viventis: In vetere teſtamento <hi>Judaei</hi> externum teplum habebant, <hi>Stephanus</hi> vero in novo ait, Excelſiſſimus ille in manufactis templis non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitat, <hi>Act.</hi> 7.46. Sicut ante dictum, Deus dixit, habitabo in eis &amp; inambulabo, &amp; ero ipſis Deus, &amp; illi erunt mihi Populus, Corpora enim veſtra ſunt templa Dei viventis, &amp; Spiritus Sancti. Hanc itaque notitiam Chriſtiani ſibi fide familiarem reddere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, <hi>Paulus</hi> ad hunc modum loquitur, An ignoratis vos eſſe Templum Dei, &amp; Spiritum Dei in vobis habitare? ſiquis Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plum Dei violat, hunc perdet Deus, nam Templum Dei Sanctum eſt, quod eſtis vos, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16.17. Omnes itaque qui Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anitatem profitentur inhabitantem in ſe Dei Spiritum ſimulque ipſorum Corpora eſſe Dei viventis templa vere cognoſcere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent quae ne polluantur ſumma cura eſt adhibenda: Ne Dei ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu pereant qui Sanctus eſt, qui &amp; ſanctitatem ab omnibus ſuis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectat. Chriſtus Phariſaeis ſummis veteris Teſtamenti Cultoribus dixit, regnum Dei non venire ut obſervari poſſet, neque dicent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104396:6"/>
ecce hic aut ecce illic, ecce enim regnum Dei intus habetis, <hi>Luc.</hi> 17.20, 21. Hinc diſcite, voſmet Explorate an Regnum Dei in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus in vobis ſitis experti: Chriſti ſententia eſt, Regnum Coelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſimile eſſe fermento, quod acceptum mulier, indidit in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinae ſata tria uſquequo fermentaretur tota, eſtque ſimile Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Coelorum grano ſinapis quod acceptum quiſpiam ſevit in agro ſuo: Hoc igitur pacto, vos qui Chriſtiani appellamini voſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met tentate, num Regnum hoc Margaritam pretioſam in agro veſtro abditam offenderitis. Agite candela accenſa, verſaque domo, theſaurus hic vaſis veſtris terrenis indubitanter a vobis eſt inveniendus qui eum extra vos hactenus quaeſiviſtis. Inde fiet ut fermentum Regni ad animas corda &amp; mentes in Maſſam Coeleſtem fermentandum cognoſcatis, ut eſt apud <hi>Matt.</hi> 13. &amp; <hi>Luc.</hi> 15. Apoſtoli quoque ſententia eſt, neminem niſi Spiritum Dei, quae Dei ſunt percipere poſſe: Nos vero non Spiritum Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di accepimus, ſed Spiritum qui eſt ex Deo, ut ſciamus quae Deus nobis gratificatus eſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.11.12.</p>
                  <p>Si modo Chriſtiani Deum, Chriſtum, &amp; quae Deus ipſis gratis abſque mercede aut pretio largitur, rite cognoſcere velint, Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum Dei in ſemetipſis operantem, teſtari neceſſe habent. Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us proclamat, Heus, quis uis ſitit, venite ad aquas iſtas, &amp; vos quibus nulla eſt Pecunia, venite, comparate abſque Pecunia &amp; abſque Pretio, Vinum &amp; Lac: Cur expenditis pecuniam pro nullo cibo, &amp; laborem veſtrum pro re minime ſatiatura? Auſcul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate indeſinenter mihi &amp; comedite bonum, atque oblectet ſe hac pinguedine anima veſtra; inclinate aurem veſtram, &amp; venite ad me, audite ut vivat anima veſtra, <hi>Jeſch.</hi> 45.22. Deus enim Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritum ſuum in omnem carnem effudit, ut per eum, Dominum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiciant, ſalutemque ſuam adipiſcantur. Deus item dicit Omnes Terrae fines Salutem intuebuntur Dei, quod futurum eſt per Spiritum, nam Deus Spiritus eſt: Inquit Dominus, Juſtitia mea in ſaeculum erit &amp; ſalus mea in omnes Generationes, <hi>Jeſch.</hi> 51.8. Proclamat Deus per <hi>Jeſchaiam,</hi> fortitudinem Populi ſui in hoc eſſe, ut maneant, nempe in Spiritu &amp; Potentia Dei, <hi>Jeſch.</hi> 30.7. Huc pertinet &amp; illud expectantes Jehovam, mutant vires, aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt pennis velut aquilae, currunt neque defatigantur, pergunt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que defetiſcuntur; In hoc ſitum eſt Solamen expectantium Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovam, quorum fortitudo in conſiſtendo ſive manendo ponitur, nam hoc pacto Dominum ſalutem ipſorum intuebuntur; omnes Filii tui edocti erunt a Jehovah, amplaque erit pax Filic <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104396:6"/>
in Juſtiſtia ſtabilientur, <hi>Jeſch.</hi> 54.13. Multa item arma in Filios Dei conficta non proſperabuntur, omneſque linguas in judicium adverſus ipſos inſurgentes qui a Domino edocti erunt, condemnabunt: Nos qui a Domino edocti ſumus (quae eſt ſua erga nos Clementia) arma multa linguaſque varias adverſum nos in judicium inſurgentes Dominum compreſſiſſe teſtamur: Deus enim ſuos ad linguas fallaces judiciaque mendacia confutandum potentia imbuit Filiolos.</p>
                  <q>De ratione Canendi &amp; Precandi.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pauli</hi> Apoſtoli ſententia de ratione Canendi &amp; Precandi haec fuit, Orabo Spiritu, ſed orabo etiam intelligentia, pſallam Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, ſed pſallam etiam intelligentia: Judae Apoſtoli ad Eccleſiam Chriſti adhortatio fuit, ut Spiritu Sancto orarent, <hi>Jud.</hi> 20. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. Libros vero unde oretur nulli commendabat Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolus, Spiritu orare &amp; intelligentia, librorum uſum nullo modo implicare videtur: Apoſtolus dicit, Spiritus ſublevat infirmita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes noſtras, quid enim oremus ut oportet non novimus, ſed ipſe Spiritus intercedit pro nobis ſuſpiriis inenarrabilibus; qui vero ſcrutatur corda, novit quid ſapiat Spiritus, quia ſecundum De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um intercedit pro ſanctis, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Ut omnes Spiritum Sanctum in cordibus, quo pro ſeipſis &amp; omnibus aliis Deum rite orent, percipiant, &amp; Dominum ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is proſequantur laudibus pro omni ſua erga ſe bonitate, quae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſaecula eſt, exoptat mihi animus ſincerus.</p>
                  <p>Apoſtolus, dixit Deus, arcana ſua nobis per Spiritum retexit, Spiritus enim omnia ſcrutatur, etiam profunditates Dei, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. Ab eodem quoque Apoſtolo dictum eſt: Juſtitia Dei per illud revelatur ex fide in fidem, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.17. Huc pertinet &amp; il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud: Notum vobis facio fratres, Evangelium quod eſt a me E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangelizatum, non eſſe ſecundum hominem, neque enim ego ab homine id accepi, neque edoctus ſum, ſed per revelationem Jeſu Chriſti, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.11, 12. Quod hinc quaerendum venit eſt hoc: Num quis Juſtitiam Dei, fidem Chriſti, Profunditates Dei, &amp; Evangelium Chriſti, niſi Spiritu Dei, haec ſibi ut olim, diebus nempe Apoſtolorum retegantur, praedicare rite valeat? Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus dixit: Quando vero libuit Deo qui ſeparavit me ab utero Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris meae, &amp; vocavit per gratiam ſuam, revelare Filium ſuum,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104396:7"/>
in me ut Evangelizarem ipſum in Gentes, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.15, 16. Chriſtus ſimiliter dicit, nemo novit Filium niſi Pater, neque Patrem quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam novit niſi Filius, &amp; cuicunque voluerit Filius ipſum rete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, <hi>Matt.</hi> 11.27. An igitur quiſquam verus Filii aut Patris Miniſter aut Praeco eſſe poteſt abſque Revelatione Divina? nam Chriſtus aperte aſſerit, neminem Patrem aut Filium niſi Spiritu revelante dignoſcere poſſe: Hinc ſeqitur, neminem nec Deum nec Chriſtum abſque Spiritus Divini revelatione Patrem &amp; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium retegente praedicare poſſe, quam quidem revelationem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum millia ſibi patefactam ad Dei perpetuum honorem teſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; qui &amp; gratis Patrem Praedicant, qui in luce illius ſicut ipſe eſt in luce ambulant, communitatem cum Patre &amp; Filio &amp; ſeinvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem mutuam obtinentes, ob quam Gratiae immortales Deo in ſaecula ſaeculorum hoc nomine debentur &amp; exhibentur.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Teſtimonium Scripturis conſonum, Perſecutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni vero Religionis cauſa maxime contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium. Sive conſilium de abrogandis legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Conſcientiam teneram Dei, Proeroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivam, conſtringentibus Christianis propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitum &amp; oblatum.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HAMAN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S</hi> Judaeos ſtirpitus evellere cupiens, eo quod Cultus eorum Religioſus <hi>Ahaſuero</hi> Regi contrarius eſſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deretur, ipſe de medio fuit ſublatus, hac pronunciata Sententia Regi in rem non eſſe ut viverent: Regi vero aliter viſum erat, qui ipſis vitam permiſit quod in rem ſuam cedere liquido cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neret.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:104396:7"/>
                     <p>Chriſtus increpatis de Coelo ignem advocantibuts ad illos perdendos qui Chriſtum accipere nolebant, dixit, neſcitis cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam Spiritus eſtis: An igitur Spiritum ſuum percipiebant qui jam inde ab Apoſtolorum diebus necandis hominibus Religionis cauſa incumbebant, qui non ſolum ignem de Coelo ad alios peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendos ſunt comprecati, verum etiam rogos in Terris conſtruen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos ob id ipſum curarunt. Annon qui talia perpetrant majore increpatione ſunt digni utpote animis magis coeci quam qui ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem de Coelo advocabant ad illos cremando, qui Chriſtum reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere nolebant? Legimus Chriſtum flagello e funiculis facto Emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores &amp; Venditores ex Templo Dei ejeciſſe, nunquam vero ad intrandum adegiſſe: Chriſtus quoque dixit ſinite Zizania &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticum una creſcere uſque ad meſſem, qui finis Mundi eſt, ne triticum eradicetur, &amp; in fine Mundi Chriſtus Angelos ſuos, Meſſores emittet, annon Angeli Spiritus ſunt &amp; non homines? Chriſtus Petrum, Gladium in vaginam recondere juſſit, addens, omnes qui Gladio uſi fuerint, Gladio peribunt.</p>
                     <p>An vero poſtea Petrus aut Apoſtolorum quiſquam, ſtricto Gladio Carnali aut armis Carnalibus, quibus Eccleſiam Chriſti, Cultum religioſum aut fidem defenderent, uſi ſunt? Contra vero Petrus Chriſti juſſu gladium recondidit &amp; Chriſtus auriculam ſervi Pontificis amputatam ſanavit, quod Evangelium ſalutare aperte deſignabat. Apoſtoli dicebant, Arma noſtrae militiae non ſunt carnalia, ſed ſpiritualia, &amp; quod nec adverſus carnem nec ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinem luctemur. Annon omnes Chriſtiani (nomine tenus) ab Apoſtolorum diebus Eccleſias, Cultum rationes, armis Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalibus utentes, adverſus Carnem &amp; Sanguinem colluctati ſunt? Annon arma militiaque eorum Carnalia, non vero ſpiritualia, cujuſmodi arma Apoſtolorum, Eccleſiaeque Chriſti Primae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vae, fuere? Qui igitur gladium quo Cultuuum rationes fideique formulas defendant, eduxerunt, non eodem quo Apoſtoli ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu praediti fuerunt, Apollyonis vero ſpiritum ſapiebant.</p>
                     <p>Annon qui hanc Scripturam producebant ad Perſecutionem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis cauſa protegendam eadem abuſi ſunt, quae ſic ſe habet, omnis anima Poteſtatibus ſupereminentibus ſubjecta eſto; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inde ſubjecti eſtote cuivis humanae ordinationi propter Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ad ultionem facinoroſorum deſtinatae, hos etlam facinoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſos nominat nempe Homicidas, Patricidas, Matricidas, Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dioſos, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> non tamen dicit, omnis anima Poteſtatibus ſuperemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentibus,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104396:8"/>
&amp; cuivis humanae ordinationi ſubjecta eſto, ut inde occaſio arripiatur homines Religionis cauſa morte mulctandi, quod hujus vel illius Coetus religioſi communitate non utantur. Si enim Apoſtolus ita ſenſiſſet: Cur, ipſe Judaeorum Caeſariſque Romani Imperatoris Religioni, ut &amp; Dianae Epheſinae ſemet non ſubmiſit? Apoſtolus Eccleſiae Chriſti dicit diſerte non eſſe tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendas aut guſtandas Doctrinas, praeſcripta &amp; ordinationes ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manas; tantum abſuerunt Chriſtiani ut ſeſe iis aut Ethnicis ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jicerent, cum in mandatis haberent talia non eſſe tangenda aut guſtanda, quae omnia ipſo uſu ſunt corrumpenda: Legimus in Apocalipſi Johannis Beſtiam Draconis Potentia ſtipatam fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe, qui omnibus in unum a ſummo ad infimum vi compulſis Ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, ipſiuſque imaginem receptam, ſuam &amp; Religionem colere adegit, Beſtiam vere ibidem in lacum igne ardentem detruſam fuiſſe, non minus obſervare licet.</p>
                     <p>Johannes ibidem teſtatur ſanguinem Prophetarum, &amp; Jeſu mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum inventum fuiſſe in Babylone Myſterio, Scortationum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaeque Adulterinae Matre ſanctorum Sanguine, &amp; Martyrum Jeſu inebriata, incolas Terrae ſuae ſcortationis vino infatuante, ebrios fuiſſe; unde tanta in ſanctos rabies Martyreſque Jeſu pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manavit, quem vero exitum ſortita ſit Meretrix illa ab eodem Johanne-literis proditum eſt.</p>
                     <p>Durantibus decem Perſecutionibus, legimus quantum Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anis excidium ab Ethnicis Regibus &amp; Imperatoribus ſit illatum, eo quod religioſo eorum cultui ſeſe adjungere aut conformes eſſe negarent. Annon plurimi intereſt Chriſtianorum, ut ſe poſitis armis Carnalibus, Gladiiſque materialibus in vaginas recondi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis quibus Cultus religioſi ab interitu, ſed fruſtra hactenus, vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carunt, &amp; armis ſpiritualibus quibus Apoſtoli uſi ſunt, uti? nec eſſe immemores Veteris Caini in Exemplum propoſiti, qui erra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundus factus, fide vera poſthabita Abelem juſtum occidebat; nec minus Iſhmael memoria eſt removendus, qui ſobolis legitimae in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſectator fuit Lethalis: Apoſtolus teſtatur, qui ex Carne natus eſt, ex ſpiritu natum perſecutus eſt, ita &amp; nunc eſt; Nuſquam vero legimus quemquam, ſecundum Spiritum natum alios perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutum eſſe: Chriſti Conſilium fuit: Inimicos diligite; mutuum amorem colite: Hinc innoteſcet vos eſſe Diſcipulos meos; qui enim Chriſtianitatem profitentur, debent praecepta Chriſti ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervare: Nebuchadonozor, Praeconem clamare juſſit, ut ſi quis
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104396:8"/>
imaginem a ſe erectam incurvatus non colat, in fornacem igne ardentem conjicitor: Deus vero fruſtrato hominis propoſito Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum ſuum incolumem ſervavit: Dominus deinde &amp; palam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit Altiſſimum in regnis hominum regnare. Nullus dehinc prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co inter Chriſtianos ſub poena concremationis, ſuſpendii, Incarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rationis, bonorum abripiendorum proclamet recuſantibus ſeſe incurvare, aut abnegantibus Ideam Religionis a ſua alienam ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orare: Haec enim non poteſt eſſe Religio vera, quia Chriſtus nihil tale uſpiam praecepit, qui Diſcipulos ad Evangeliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ndum omnibus Gentibus emiſit, ſed non ſub poena Concremationis, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpendii, Patibuli, incarcerationis, aut honorum abripiendorum eis denunciata, qui id aut ipſos recipere reſpuebant. Pulvis vero Pedum eorum die noviſſimo firmum ad id evincendum Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium eſſe voluit.</p>
                     <p>Pharaoh cum exercitu ſuo ingenti Perſecutor, liberorumque Enecator Crudelis fuit, quem vero finem ille cum exercitu habu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, palam eſt; Annon in mare divinitus immiſſo ſui Populi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiriis a Jehovah auditis, peribat?</p>
                     <p>Nec minus atrox Domini cultorum Perſecutor fuit Herodes, qui infantulos necandos curavit, nec defuit voluntas Chriſtum ipſum mortis ſupplicio afficiendi; Deus vero ipſum ex ipſius ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu eruit: Tempus nunc poſtulat ut ſepoſita Religionis cauſa Perſecutione, utpote Dei voluntate contraria Apoſtolo dictanti auſcultemus, qui ad hunc modum loquitur: Qui fratrem odio proſequitur, homicida eſt, nec habet vitam aeternam in ſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentem, qui vero in Charitate habitat in Deo habitat, nam De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Charitas eſt. Davidi olim Templum externum aedificare ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fas fuit, quod ſanguinem in bellis externis ſub veteri foedere effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſet: Quomodo ergo vos ſpiritus pacifici ductum ignorantes, quorum opera tot caedes perſonarum, violationes bonorum Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionis cauſa, direptiones perpetratae fuere, Templum ſpirituale ſub novo foedere condere poteſtis? Zion ſub veteri pacto ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis diſpendio non erat conſtruenda; an igitur verſimile eſt, Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolimam Coeleſtem ſub novo foedere a Chriſtianis, ita dictis ſanguinis effuſione, Perſecutione, Carceratione, bonorum abrep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionibus aedificatum iri, quum Chriſtus ipſe palam eis teſtatus eſt, qui ignem de Coelo ad homines necandos advocabant: Neſcitis inquit quem Spiritum ſapiatis. Quo pacto igitur dignoſcere po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtis quem ſpiritum vos ſapiatis, qui occiditis, ad necem in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104396:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
carceribus, bonis abripiendis, idque de rebus fidei, Eccleſiae &amp; Cultus religioſi inſectati eſtis atrociter?</p>
                     <p>Quam igitur periculoſum eſt illis, vel corporum nedum anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum curam concredere, qui quem ſpiritum ſapiant, ignorant. Jeſus Chriſtus turbam ſaepiſſime allocutus eſt, qui aures habet ad audiendum, audiat; neminem vero auditu Orbatum, nec illos qui aures obdurabant, ne audiant, nec Oculos praecludentes, ne videant &amp; convertantur, perſecutus eſt; nec ullum a Cultu ſuo religioſo, aut Religione abhorrentem, in Carcerem detruſit: aut quod cultui ab ipſo inſtituto minime conformes eſſent, bona abripienda praecepit: Saepius vero dixit, qui aurem habet, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diat, &amp; ita auribus ipſos commendabat: Johannes in Apocalyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi ſeptem Eccleſiis dicit, qui aurem habet, audiat quid Spiritus dicat Eccleſiis, non vero dicit, qui aurem non habet, ad audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endum, quid Spiritus dicat Eccleſiis, aut conformis eſſe reſpue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; in Carcerem conjicitor, bona iſtiuſmodi hominis abrini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur, vel in exilium mittatur; neque enim Chriſtus, neque ab illo Apoſtoli, nihil tale uſpiam praeceperunt: Chriſti mandatum ſic ſe habet: Voſmet mutuo amore proſequimini: inimicos dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gite, qui enim in amore habitat in Deo habitat, &amp; qui fratrem odit eſt homicida, nullus vero homicida vitam habet aeternam in ſe manentem: Johannes itidem in Apocalypſi dicit Beſtiam fuiſſe Draconis potentia munitam, qui omnes a minimis ad maximos ad ſe imaginemque ſuam colendum adegiſſe: Annon ibidem le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere licet Beſtiam, Draconem, eorumque Aſſeclas &amp; Cultores in Lacum flagrantem deturbatos fuiſſe? Annon igitur magni inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chriſtianorum ut Apoſtolorum armis ſpiritualibus, ſibi aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptis, quibus ſolummodo fides, Eccleſia &amp; Cultus Divinus propagatur, &amp; reſipiſcant, &amp; ad frugem meliorem ſeſe recipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant?</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
